hmm okay so
okay so
the subject i thought it would be good
to speak about
comes down to a type of
to call it a view might be misleading
it's more like a kind of
axiom of thought that is really taken
for granted
and that can be expressed in
a few different ways but it comes down
to like the idea that
there's no such thing as
certainty in regard to really the nature
of things
there's no such thing as
sort of absolute knowledge and it will
come it's not usually something that
people will state like explicitly it's
implied but it's implied in
their thoughts their ideas
and sometimes you know you'd be having a
conversation with somebody about for
example right and wrong or something and
just when it seems like it's starting to
go somewhere
then they say oh well you can never
really know can you
yeah well it's almost like the agnosticism in
well it's almost like the agnosticism in
the suttas
people have like what they deem to be
sort of like a conventional knowledge
but then if you start pushing it towards
the further clarity it's all
it's taken as valid
uh this kind of dismissal a while you
can't really know
and that's that's but it's like well you
obviously seem to think that you know
that you obviously seem to think that you
you obviously seem to think that you
know that you can't really know but okay
so if your premise is true how do you
know that how do you know that you can't
know and then you realize it's a
and then you realize it's a
contradiction in terms yeah
yeah so that's one thing is like the
statement in order to be true must be false
in order to be true must be false
because if you apply it to itself yeah
um
and about this there was a few things that
about this there was a few things that
i kind of wanted to
bring up about it because
it's
it's really something that a lot of
people seem to subscribe to and it's
like you can see that if you kind of take the
you can see that if you kind of take the
notion of knowledge
in a kind of scientific sense as in
we need to know things about the world
by gathering information and data about
them then
then
you do have to say well whatever we can
find out
has to be you know it can always be
disproved by something
you never can absolutely know
because why do you think that is
why do you think that is
because
the data that you can gather and the
information that you can gather depends
on the instrument through which you are
exactly so it's purely observational based on
so it's purely observational based on
the senses which means
all you need to do in order to disprove
it is find something observe something
different that's it that's it
and the the even bigger problem like in
itself as a method of learning about the
world that's fine but
your mind is not an object of your
senses cannot be the objective senses
yet if your only criteria for learning
and understanding is gathering
information through the observation on
the basis of your senses means the
entire domain of your mind and mental
development is absolutely
excluded from any recognition
yeah and it occurred to me that that
also um is
you know it's not something that's
exclusive to
science in that way i mean the same
type of basing
one's ideas with views on this kind of
ideas with views on this kind of
information that one gathers i mean in
let's say um
you know that's it i think it's brahmana
jealous of the end where he's like going
through all of these all of the
views that different people can have
and they have a huge variety of views
based on
like different
types of information that they gather i
mean you have one who's
been able to remember 40 eons of past
lives or something so that's like
unbelievable amount of information yeah
that he has
but then the problem is like that he
then goes to say well that's the
information i have therefore that's how
the world is the world itself is eternal
so yeah exactly yeah
and and
and
the other thing i wanted to bring up
about it is that
it is one way of expressing what the
wrong view it seems to me like the when
he says there are no monks and brahmins
who know the world and
know the world and
understand the nature of the world and
declare it like that
certainty direct knowledge
is not a possibility
and
to me that also seems like um
you know that's one aspect of this wrong
view that the buddha describes but when
i think about it i can see that it also
implies the rest of the
the that description of the wrong view
because if you're saying when somebody
says like i'm talking to somebody and
they say well you can never really know
you never have any certainty
then you know
you know
it means for them that's
well whatever i might do
whatever i might kind of strive for
i'm never going to ever
know for sure whether it's right or
wrong i'm never going to know for sure
like um
um
what's the result of it so like
ultimately in a fundamental sense everything that i
in a fundamental sense everything that i
do is sort of i'll just hope for the
best i hope for the dude
best of the abilities
what do you think why do you think they
do that
what is the practical basis because
there's always a practical basis for
every wrong view practical i mean
some sort of
involvement that you try to where you're
not admitting to yourself so in this
particular case what what would the
practical basis for their view be
why would somebody
prefer to hold a view of well you can't really
to hold a view of well you can't really
know anything or not you can't be 100
sure so
because when you start thinking
that there might be the possibility but there
there might be the possibility but there
is the possibility there could be the
possibility of direct knowledge
certainty knowledge of right and wrong
then you can't be really indifferent
about that you have to do something
about it and you can or feel guilty for
not doing it either way you can't cover
up the the weight the weight of it yeah
that's exactly that's why it's always
wrong views and
inauthenticity hand in hand always you
cannot be authentic and hold the wrong
views nor can you remain inauthentic if
you're dropping the wrong views that's
impossible yeah
yeah and it's
i also found it interesting because
you know at some point i used to think i
used to kind of not pay that much
attention to the description of the
wrong view that the
buddha was
giving and
and
like i've heard people say that it's
just this sort of
oh some people in that time had these
extreme views oh yeah yeah yeah
it tends to be sort of um
like dumbed down and assumed it was like a
dumbed down and assumed it was like a
almost like caricature examples
like oh yeah the eternalists and the
annihilationists we are past that point there's like no
we are past that point there's like no
those are the two fundamental
existential views for as long as you're
not a satan
so you're going to be either a
journalist or an isolationist there is
no third option for you there all the
variety of the views that brahmajala
sutra elaborates on fall into these two
categories you want to say yes and one
say no
they don't see the middle
yeah and
at least yeah to me the
the problem as well with kind of
thinking that it's a you know
these views like the wrong view under
the its counterpart as well the right
view are to be found in what somebody
expressly explicitly
believes and professes i think
such and such a thing
and [Music]
[Music]
i think it's a problem because then it
would mean that you just kind of get
let's say the the the mundane as it's
called right view or such or something
like that by sort of just adopting a
particular set of ideas yeah
yeah like as far as the the right view
is a view
but obviously
it's a view that goes
in between
the the two kind of polar opposites of wrong
the two kind of polar opposites of wrong
views yes and no annihilation is
journalists
mystics or scientifically oriented
doesn't matter
the right view is the view that puts
first at first and everything else is
second so it's uh it's not
so it's uh it's not
it's not directly opposed to the wrong
views in the sense of left to the right
it's more like left right are both wrong
and this is above the right view is
above both that's why going beyond the
wrong views through a right view and
eventually for another hunt who has
brought the right view to like
fulfillment he has gone even beyond that
vertical view of right perspective he
has dropped everything in that sense
so
yeah i think initially
uh people will take
the right view
in a wrong sense
through some sort of belief or faith and
that's inevitable inevitable
but
and that in itself is not a problem the
problem is if then they
think that's it that's all they needed
to do just let me assume the right
things on the base of information i
collected which yes it might be
factually less wrong than other views
you had before
but the measure of the right view
it's not the measure of your belief
faith confidence certainty is the
measure it's measured by your inability
to suffer
so and that's something you you can't
really lie i mean you can obviously
cover it up but fundamentally you're
always aware
of it as a problem
like the fact that you're not free from
suffering and you know it
and if that's the case means you can't
you shouldn't be
deluding yourself into thinking but i
still have a right view because if you
did you wouldn't be afraid of suffering
anymore you would you wouldn't be you wouldn't
you would you wouldn't be you wouldn't
be affected by the suffering anymore not
to the no to like a
maybe to some tiny degree let's say like
that from the arahant's point of view
yes you would be affected by suffering
as a sotapanna but from put together's
point of view well you're pretty much on
the level of our hunger as far as
protection is concerned because he has
no knowledge of any escape from
suffering and that's that the fundamental
and that's that the fundamental
difference
somebody who
who
without knowing is
has wrong views underlying their
wrong views underlying their
actions and their what they're doing
um
[Music] can they practice the dharma
you mean the actual
the actual dharma no no that's
impossible so even if they let's say i try to be
so even if they let's say i try to be
very virtuous
all that's commendable and to be
encouraged but
it's the right view that makes dhamma
visible and if you're not seeing what you're
and if you're not seeing what you're
supposed to be doing then you are you're
not doing it
uh and even if you're going through all
the right motions
that's when you realize how he's doing
it for the wrong reasons he's doing the
right things for the wrong reasons
it's still better than doing wrong
things for the wrong reasons but
fundamentally the dhamma only arises with the right
the dhamma only arises with the right
view
and again it's important to just
not lie to yourself about it
because if you think you have access to dhamma
if you think you have access to dhamma
the actual dharma the actual path to
liberation the buddhist teaching without
being a sort of owner
that's it you already think you already
basically assumed that you have
gained the access to to the result of
your right view
without the right view which means
you're not going to recognize the
importance and the severity of having
wrong views and the importance of
actually needing to get the right view
because there is no dhamma below that
and people would ignore the importance
and would not make the effort for the
same reason we said in the beginning oh
as nothing can be you can't be sure
because that would then make them like
too unpleasant feel too unpleasantly
about it because it is
it is a serious weight burden and
especially if you don't know what to do
about it and now you're even more
overwhelmed with the confusion it's like
well that's at least a good starting point
that's at least a good starting point
now at least you know what work needs to
be done
now at least you realize the
the problem with the position you're in
yeah yeah yeah and in order to recognize
that well in order to find a solution
for a problem you first need to stop
ignoring it i mean and you know that in
a mundane day-to-day life
when everybody's aware that this person
has a problem but that person is
refusing to admit it and nothing you do
nothing you offer nothing you just in in
in a form of help will actually help
because they refuse to acknowledge
that there is a problem
blatantly lying about it to themselves
and that's the same on the level of the
mind so unless you recognize that no no
this is a factual problem that
the only way out of this problem would
be to get the right view
then you take it seriously and then you
actually have a chance of getting the
right view and and
[Music]
that's what we're saying before like the
prerequisite for the right view
is like the right honesty or
self-honesty or transparency or
authenticity whatever you want to call
it
without it don't matter how much 50
years you can practice dummy you're not
purchasing the dharma
and can you get the right view
by
doing something other than
uh questioning your views and trying to
undo or like seeing how the wrong view is
or like seeing how the wrong view is
wrong no no because whatever you would
be doing in that case would be on the
basis of your wrong views
so you're not really uprooting or
undoing the problem you're just building
on top of it
yeah yep yep
so
just another
um
branch on the same topic that is
related to what you just said
that i've kind of
come up against is that when
people start to practice
and now they say okay i want to be
sotapanna and if i'm not a sotapanna
then i can't i can't
[Music]
say that i know
but then
so then they're kind of
the the problem is that
that people can sort of say well
there is no certainty apart from one who
is a sort of banner
um
but then they kind of don't actually
change their attitude from that basic
attitude of saying oh well nothing can
be certain
because they're kind of so they can
abstractly allow possibility of being
certain as a sort of partner but
practically they absolutely abolish it
yeah yeah that's that's quite that's
probably the most common kind of
attitude between the clay people and the
monks in a sense you're also driving they're
in a sense you're also driving they're
all striving for something
but practically
if if you know if you were to develop
clarity about it or to make the effort
or to investigate the meaning and so on
to actually start doing something about
the lack of clarity which is renting
your brains that's always dismissed as
if like wow
that's just your views and opinions on
everything that's your view and opinion
so the question is not not having any
views and opinions in that kind of
non-committal sense because you're
committing to that the question is yeah
undoing all the wrong views by seeing
how they're wrong why they're wrong
finding contradiction in them and that's
how you will be unable to hold them and
that's how you're getting closer to the
right view recognizing where the problem
is and not covering it up anymore
yeah a kind of a version of that too is
saying like okay um
i think
uh x y and z
but i'm not a sort of banner so i might
be wrong or i'm probably wrong in some
way so then i'll ask somebody else who i
think is a sort of panel and then i'll
follow up with you or not even then i
ask somebody else who might have an
opinion about it and that somehow you
know we're going to arrive at the right
conclusion yeah
yeah i heard it i don't know how many
times exactly that's like
somebody will ask a very
uh clear question practical question
and then uh
the answer they will get would be
quoting what somebody else might say in
that instance that's right
the only again in a mundane sense the
only time i would i would give you an
answer in that way like you ask me
something i say well there's this such
and such and he likes to do this in such
cases is because i don't have a clue
what i'm talking about
because if i understood what i'm talking
about i would understand your question
and i would understand the best answer
for you
even if i'm absolutely kind of
illiterate in every other way you
understand the craft you understand the
way out you will know how to convey it
and the clear indication of not knowing
the way out
when somebody asks you a question about
suffering or dhamma and you just keep
sort of throwing in references or
referring to this nothing like i'll give
you a reference to help what i just told
you but more like oh yes you know the
big senior uh ajahn he always says this he's
senior uh ajahn he always says this he's
like yeah but i didn't ask the big
senior raj i'm asking you
because you know you offered yourself
for that purpose
so that should always be a red flag
um and i remember that was always the
thing as well like
i personally kind of
from the start was you know reading the
suttas philosophy
that was my thing never really listened
to any dumber talks and so on and first
time i heard duma talks
i thought
well i i felt like there was nothing
being said it was just just people
talking for an hour giving these generic
ideas but and i thought oh maybe that's
just the form of the dhamma talk you
can't really be very specific but then
the more i listened the more
it became apparent that no you can't be
specific it's just that these people
aren't and the only reason they are not
specific is because either they don't
want to tell you which why wouldn't they
do that
or they don't know what to tell you so
you just let me feel an hour with these
inspirational terms and so on and kind
of resembling the suit that's sometimes
more something less but overall if you
to know what you're talking about you
would have a straight answer and there's
a direct suit exactly that says that
when uh
the king or whoever he was as the buddha
do you prepare the answers beforehand he
says no you are the king master chariot
he says yes i am if somebody would if
somebody were to ask you anything about
the workings of a chariot would you have
to prepare an answer he says no they
wake me in the middle of the night i'll
give him an answer immediately because i
fully understood the working god
same with the one who is basically
practice the way rightly who is
enlightened or who is on the way to be
enlightened he will be able to convey
their way at any given time
um
so it was always like a and then
obviously you know once i started talking i
you know once i started talking i
realized oh yeah no you can be very
specific and as a matter of fact the
sutas were talks that's what you know
the buddha didn't say and right
wrote down the suitors he didn't sit
down and wrote down the suitors
you know premeditating what's he going
to say it was basically recorded
conversations so there is no problem
with the medium of
of like a direct discourse the problem
is that there is no
substance to it generally
and that's like again that's found in
sutras probably often over red it's like
when when a man comes seeking heartwood
and asks a question how to find the
heartwood and then
he was given the answer about sapwood
and him the man not knowing any better
he takes the sapwood to be the heartwood
and he'll stop looking for the heartwood
and so yeah
to
so that another problem i think also is
like when somebody
needs to rely on somebody else's
views or somebody what somebody else
says because they themselves don't know
yeah and
then what can happen is that they
themselves stop take respon taking
responsibility for having like okay
so-and-so said this faith in him because
it must be right that's it and now you
it's not me thinking this anymore it's
not what i think anymore
and now even if that person is factual
buddha himself
yeah if you took the practice on that level
if you took the practice on that level
means there is no practice for you but
for as long as that doesn't change that
attitude yeah
and and so then like
and so then like
you know
it's terrible any any
anything that contradicts what you know
you have decided to have faith in
you can say oh
no no that's that can't be right
while at the same time kind of
forgetting that actually you don't know
for yourself which one is
well that's that's like one of the
um like the basic logical fallacies and
all of them have this the same thread
i don't even mention it at all but it's
all of that cover-up avoiding to take
take responsibilities so it's either you
assume the authority either some senior
monk or your teacher or the religion or
the texts or you know the scholarly
study of the dictionary you see now
that's that's that's that's it that's
factual how it's written
all done for the purpose of yeah but
what does that mean for you just like
the difference in the buddha after talks
about the sort of the phrasing and the
meaning yeah the meaning you won't find in the
yeah the meaning you won't find in the
phrasing
like self-evident
you need to actually undo your wrong
views for these subtle meanings to
become because everybody reads the
suitors but almost nobody gets the right view on
but almost nobody gets the right view on
account of reading the sutras why is
that either the suitors are wrong or
the instruments that people are reading
the suitors with the views the what they
perceive the concepts that everything
else implied in it it's completely
covered like layers and layers and
layers of
of yeah the the
the wrong views that the buddha listen
in brahmajala sutra
and that's why
there is no meaning becoming apparent
does it kind of um maybe come down to
the difference between
okay it's my aim
to genuinely
go beyond doubt
or is it to
like become a sort of fan according to
my idea of what
somebody said sort of that's going to be
the first thing like i want to become
certified as a suit to say oh such and
such became silicon well if he can do it
i can do it type of thing
so yeah it's taken wrongly but it does
sort of
aim in the broader sense in the right
direction but then yes you could spend
next as i said five decades of just
protecting that view and that and not
really uh recognizing or stepping further into
uh recognizing or stepping further into
understanding what actually means to be
a certifier oh i want to become a
surprise and i'm doing all these things
but why do you do what you're doing
why are you doing these practices why
are you even keeping the virtue what
like do you understand or you do or
you're just doing all of that because
you were told to
and that would be the difference then if
somebody's actually getting closer to
become a certified one who starts
questioning all these things
and trying to understand them
then inevitably you're going to arrive
at the doubt
and in
in
understanding what the actual problem of
the doubt is it's not what you're
doubting is the presence of the discomfort of the
is the presence of the discomfort of the
doubt
and again that's something you can
theories about it but it will never be
right until you actually start enduring
it and
yeah because people can kind of think
well okay uh
being becoming a sort of partner will
free me from doubt rather than it being
freeing myself from doubt will make me
so tapana yep that's exactly it yeah
the horse or the cart
people put the cart in front of the
horse and think oh let me just do these
and think oh let me just do these
practices they will result in my magical
awakening of sort of party and then
these fatters will fall off
my self-view doubt and
virtue and duty and so on
but uh it's other way around
it's you
fully understanding these factors is how
you become a sort of owner
so you understanding the virtue and duty
and freeing yourself from that
assumption of it freeing yourself from
assuming the external
sense of self outside of your experience
and freeing yourself from the pressure
of the doubt
uh and then when these three factors
don't move you
it's safe to say you're a satan
not other way around
it's interesting how
even like the
ideas that people have about the dhamma
can be used to
sort of justify holding
the wrong views
in
i'm thinking of an example where
you know somebody might say
okay no this is how it is this is how it
can be discerned directly in your
experience and then the response was
and then the response was
well no because you know that's not a
ground for being sure about it because
you know protogenera sees self in his
experience so like the idea that
there is
there's not supposed to be a self
well it's it's it's on that kind of arms
length level like where do people yes
it's possible it's it's it's never taken
on that personal level because again
it's gonna
fatters are not seen
are not seen
because people avoid
seeing them or admitting them because
they are unpleasant
like the reason why everybody
so easily assumes external duty and
virtue and practice and method and
technique is because it's easier
than to leave it non-specific and then
feel the burden of confusion and
everything i'm doing right am i doing
wrong what do i do how do i do it or
fundamentally if you stay in that state
you would recognize oh my only concern
here with this entire state is that it's
unpleasant and i refuse to accept that
discomfort of it that's why i'm worried
about what to do not because i really
need to know what to do and more often
not you actually know what you need to
do
but if when the pain pressures you you
doubt everything because your primary
concern is aversion to its pain must be
avoided always that pain must be you
know dealt with instantly
and that's why you get
then liable to doubt and everything else
because you gave it power
and not even seeing that you know what
you're doing is trying to avoid the pain
of it because your mind is focused on i
have to solve this your question in this
problem and
and
related to that actually like another
another thing i noticed about this kind
of
thing that people end up coming down to
i said oh well you know i can't be sure
about that or that you can't really be
certain about this thing is this
it can be kind of used to uh justify
uh
holding let's say you have an idea um
about right and wrong for example like usually
right and wrong for example like usually
and this i'm not to go into kind of
specific ideas of right and wrong but it
usually would kind of be like on the
level of a
a specific template
of how the world should look and how
people should behave and should act and
it should be like this and etc
that this is right and then anything
that's but then you kind of it come you
come to the point of realizing well
that's nothing i do will ever be able to create
nothing i do will ever be able to create
that template how i want it to be it
can't be quite it's always out of reach
exactly and instead of then realizing well my
and instead of then realizing well my
idea of what is
right and wrong might be flawed or might
be wrong yeah it's like oh well
you can't ever be perfect exactly yeah
just try your best and that's it
but uh
yeah even that then becomes just a
coping coping mechanism
because if you realize you are trying
your best and still
nothing changes in the way things don't
matter then you either just
then you either just
dismiss that or you reckon as well maybe
you know
my best efforts are completely
misdirected and that's the painful thing where the
and that's the painful thing where the
honesty comes in if you start admitting
it you realize yeah because if my
tenth of these efforts that i have been
making factually were actually directed
to the things
that matter such as freedom from
suffering greed aversion delusion if you
made effort to to clarify that and not
act out of it and everything else we
talk about you know oh yeah
i would have had the results i'm hoping
for but
but
yeah it's um
people are easily misled
because they already are misleading
themselves through not being honest
enough why are you doing what you're doing
why are you doing what you're doing
uh and why are you holding views that
you're holding
and it's much easier instead of that is
so unpleasant to kind of uh accept the
possibility that everything that i've
been doing and all the efforts i've been
making might have been in the wrong
direction or perhaps but it's
it's so it's much easier than to kind of
yeah say fall back on this
oh well it can never be quite perfect
and like nothing i do
again like there there are no fruits and
results ultimately of good and bad
action exactly so you you failed to even
grasp the mundane right view
and that's exactly i mean i've seen i've
seen senior monks saying that after you
know i don't know i said decades in robe
giving dhamma talks and saying like no
no no
and i don't mean they're speaking
poetically they spend an hour explaining
what they meant and what they what they
were saying was oh there's nothing to be
attained like all these all these things about
like all these all these things about
you know getting so no no it's not it's
not about attaining anything don't worry
about becoming a social partner don't worry
becoming a social partner don't worry
about it just you know be here now and
and then the whole thing the whole talk
revolves around that concept of how
don't do anything just accept yourself
the way you are i was like but you are a
patina if you accept yourself as somebody who
if you accept yourself as somebody who
is drowning means you will never gonna
save yourself you will drown oh yeah i
accept the fact that i'm drowning okay
fine goodbye then
oh no i don't accept the fact that i'm
drowning i'm gonna at least try and get
out of this this quicksand or whatever
i'm in
well now you at least have a chance
because you're trying
but i'm sure that none of those those
those senior teachers started with that
view they probably had more or less genuine
they probably had more or less genuine
view in the beginning
but having been going wrongly about it
you end up covering it up more and more
and more and obviously the more you go
in that direction
the further away you drift from even
basic honesty on that existential level
and then
it becomes easier to then even just just
just blatantly cover up or dismiss or
like not even consider whether that
might contradict the suitors and so on
because well you know look i've been 50
years doing this and yeah i'm fine i'm a
good person it's not about being a good
person it's about ceasing to be a person
it's about freeing yourself from entire
samsara you want to be a good person
fine but that's not
what the dharma teaches that's like
somebody who can't practice the dumb
okay at least be a good person
but if you can practice the dharma that
that is the goal
so again
people come and look up to those you
know teachers or or or teachings
teachers or or or teachings
to find the heartwood to find the source
of the the meaning the core of the of
the of the teaching and all they get is
kind of irrelevant bach and set food and
stuff that's useless or it's just
um relatively useful
for for mundane matters so
so
if there was nothing to be attained
would have buddha would have the buddha
talked about it often
you know if if it's all about just being
here and now and accepting you know not
judging and whatever else the buddha
would have surely mentioned that
no no he does not tolerate he doesn't
welcome he doesn't act out he creates
his feet and endures it and use the
elements and use the words of others
purifies his mind from the states day
and night takes responsibilities virtues
sends restraint
doesn't look for loopholes
so there's plenty to do
yet your conclusion from all of that is
right right okay be here now and just
relax and you know
calm down and that's it it's all fine
there's no problem you are the one
creating problems
yeah because problems are there
because problems are there
it can seem that you are creating them
by looking at them so what the child
does when it's scared or doesn't want to
deal when it covers its eyes
thinking okay i don't see it it's not
there anymore
but if it were not there why would you
have to cover your eyes in the beginning